<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tribunall of the conscience: or, A treatise of examination shewing vvhy and how a Christian should examine his conscience, and take an account of his life. By Henry Mason, parson of St. Andrews Vndershaft, London.</title>
            <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112441</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847695</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847695</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1074:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tribunall of the conscience: or, A treatise of examination shewing vvhy and how a Christian should examine his conscience, and take an account of his life. By Henry Mason, parson of St. Andrews Vndershaft, London.</title>
                  <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G[eorge] P[urslowe] for Iohn Clarke, and are to be sold at his shop, vnder St. Peters Church in Corne-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience, Examination of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12751:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12751:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12751:2"/>
            <p>THE TRIBVNALL OF THE CONSCIENCE: <hi>OR,</hi> A TREATISE OF <hi>EXAMINATION;</hi> SHEWING Why and how a Chriſtian ſhould <hi>examine his Conſcience, and take</hi> an account of his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> HENRY MASON, Parſon of St. <hi>Andrews Vnderſhaft,</hi> London.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, vnder St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Corne-hill.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12751:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12751:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> THOMAS COVENTRY, Knight, <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> of the great Seale of ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot long ſince I publiſhed a ſmall Treatiſe concerning <hi>Faſting:</hi> and therein, the matter giuing me occaſion for it, I mentioned ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duties, fit (as I thought) to bee practiſed vpon a faſting-day; as namely <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of our liues, <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of our ſinnes, and a ſtedfaſt <hi>purpoſe</hi> of a better life. But theſe being there but named only, becauſe the handling of them was not proper to that place: ſome haue deſired a more full direction for the right performance of thoſe holy duties. And becauſe <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Conſcience is one of them, and
<pb facs="tcp:12751:4"/>ſuch a one, as doth leade and direct and carry with it all the reſt; I was vpon this occaſion perſwaded to reuiſe ſome Notes, which lay by mee, concerning that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and thence I haue framed this ſhort Treatiſe, which I therefore call the <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the Conſcience,</hi> becauſe the worke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended is a kinde of judiciary proceeding, wherein a mans conſcience doth giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vpon himſelfe. And this little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe concerning the iudgement of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, I haue made bold to offer to your Lordſhips Patronage and Protection, who by your Office are <hi>IVDGE</hi> of the Court of Conſcience: hoping that hauing your Name in the Front, it may finde the more fauour abroad; and nothing doubting, but if it finde entertainement, it will returne ſome part of thankfulneſſe to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip backe againe, by eaſing you and your Court of friuolous, tedious and vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous quarels. For if Plaintifes would exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their conſcience concerning the iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their cauſe, and the reaſonableneſſe of their demands, it would make them to
<pb facs="tcp:12751:4"/>relinquiſh their cauilling ſuites before they did commence them. And if Defendants would examine their conſcience concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the wrongs they haue done, and the dues which they owe, it would make them to giue a willing ſatisfaction, rather than to weary their neighbour with vniuſt and ſhifting delaies. And if Lawyers would examine their conſcience concerning ſuch rules as Religion doth tye them to, in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for mens rights, it would make them to turne away ſuch Clients, as brought them vnreaſonable cauſes. And if Iudges would examine their conſcience, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the duties of their place, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the ſuites that euery day are deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Court, it would make them ſo to entertaine all ſorts of wranglers, as that they would haue no great luſt to bring fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous matters before a righteous Iudge. And ſo at length it might bee hoped, that that might happen in your Lordſhips time, which they ſay did happen in the time of Sir <hi>Thomas More,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stapleto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de tribus Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, in vita Tho. Mori, cap.</hi> 3.</note> Who</hi> (as mine Author ſaith) <hi>hauing ended a cauſe then before him,
<pb facs="tcp:12751:5"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12751:5"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12751:6"/>did call for the next to be brought: but anſwer was returned him, that there was neuer ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe behinde.</hi> And ſo the Court was diſmiſſed, becauſe there were no more cauſes to be heard. A great honour to the Iudge, and a great happineſſe to the people. The like honour and happineſſe I ſhall euer pray may once happen in your Lordſhips dayes; that ſo conſcience preuailing, wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling ſuites may haue an end. And heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, continuing my prayers alſo for your Lordſhips proſperitie, together with the peace of a good conſcience; I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours deuoted in all ſeruice, <hi>HENRIE MASON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12751:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> TRIBVNALL OF THE CONSCIENCE: <hi>OR</hi> A Treatiſe of <hi>Examination;</hi> Shewing why and how a Chriſtian ſhould <hi>examine his conſcience, and take an account of his life.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Hiſtorie of the Creation, it is ſaid, that at the daies end GOD looked vpon the worke that hee had made, and hee
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 1.4, 10, 12, 18, 21, 25.</note> 
               <hi>ſaw that it was good:</hi> and at the end of the weeke, taking a view of all his workes together,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen. 1.31</note> 
               <hi>he ſaw euery thing that hee had made, and behold it was very good.</hi> Which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that after God had done his workes, hee did reflect vpon them, and conſidered the quality and the condition of them. In imitation heereof, or in conformity hereunto, wiſe men doe wiſh vs, that at euery dayes end wee ſhould reflect vpon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12751:7"/>our works, and take a view of what we haue done that day; and at the weekes end, take account of all our doings for that ſpace of time; and ſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as further occaſion ſhall require. And this Enquirie or account-taking of our workes, they call the Examination of our ſoules or conſcience. And ſurely, if wee did obſerue this rule, ſtill to reflect vpon our ſelues after our workes are done, though we could not finde them to be like vnto Gods workes, <hi>good</hi> and <hi>very good;</hi> nay we ſhould rather finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>naught</hi> &amp; <hi>very naught:</hi> yet by this viewing and ſearching into our workes, if it bee rightly and diligently performed, we may, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, make our workes much better than they are. In regard whereof, I haue aſſaied, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by my poore labours this way, I may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſomething to the Chriſtian Reader, that may incite him to vndertake this worke willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or that may direct him how to performe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and to the profit and ſpirituall good of his ſoule. And for this purpoſe, I haue thought theſe ſix Points worthy of conſideration:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What generall Inducements there are, that may animate a Chriſtian to vndertake the ſearch and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this worke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Wherein the performance of this worke doth conſiſt, and what actions or performances it doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and containe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>What the Matter is, about which Examination is to be exerciſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>In what Manner and order it may and ought to be performed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12751:7"/>
                  <item>5. <hi>What be the Times, in which it is moſt fit to be vſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>What fruit or ſpirituall good a man may get by this Exerciſe, when it is rightly and carefully perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>What generall inducements there are, that may ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate a Chriſtian to goe about and vndertake this worke.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man vndertaketh any worke, but in hope of ſome good to be gotten by it. For, <hi>Omnis actie eſt propter finem;</hi> All actions, ſay Philoſophers, are for ſome end: and, <hi>finis et bonum conuertuntur;</hi> that which a man propoundeth to himſelfe for his end, is the good which hee hopeth to gaine. This is generally true in all actions of any value, but moſt eſpecially in ſuch as be either difficult or diſtaſtfull to our nature: for men are hardly drawne to vndergoe ſuch, but vpon good hopes that may recompence their labours; but without ſome reaſonable inducements, no man would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yeeld to take paines in difficult buſineſſes. And vpon this conſideration, being about an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe that is ſomewhat laborious in it ſelfe, and very tedious to our vntoward nature, I haue thought it neceſſary in the very entrance, and as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12751:8"/>it were by way of Preface, to conſider what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements a reaſonable man may haue to beſtow his paines both in learning and in practiſing of this duty.</p>
               <p>And for the inducements, (beſide the ſpeciall vſes and benefits that may be reaped by it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I ſhall haue fitter occaſion to ſpeake hereafter, when the nature and conditions of it be firſt laid downe and declared;) it will be ſufficient, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for this place, to conſider of ſome generall motiues: and they be theſe two eſpecially, firſt <hi>Precept,</hi> and ſecondly <hi>Practice.</hi> By Precept I meane ſuch commands as God hath impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs in Scripture, for the doing of this worke: and by Practice I meane the examples of wiſe men, who haue gone before vs in the vſe of it, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the exhortations and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which they animate and prouoke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and others to the practice of it. By the one of which it is commanded as a neceſſary duty, and by the other it is commended as a profitable worke, that may ſtead vs in the wel-ordering of our life: and by both theſe, any reaſonable man, but eſpecially euery wiſe Chriſtian may bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to vndergoe this worke, not doubting but that he is in a good way, in which ſo many wiſe and good men haue gone before him, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe of comfort and ſucceſſe in that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which God hath enioyned him. To come then to the Point.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The firſt inducement to this worke is Gods Precept or Commandement: ſuch as that is,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12751:8"/>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup.</hi> And that of the ſame Apoſtle;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Examine your ſelues, whether ye be in the faith; proue your own ſelues.</hi> And that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gal. 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Let euery man</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>proue his owne worke;</hi> or examine his own worke: for the
<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſame word is vſed in this place and the former. And ſuch alſo is that rule of <hi>Dauid;
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> Commune with your owne heart vpon your bed, and be ſtill.</hi> Vpon which words Saint <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> commenteth to this purpoſe; <hi>What is this, that he ſaith,</hi> [<hi>Commune with your owne heart, &amp;c?</hi>] Why? <hi>Dauid</hi> (ſaith he) ſpeaketh to this effect; <hi>After ſupper, when ye are going to ſleepe, —
<note n="f" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c.</note> ſet vp the iudgement ſeate of the conſcience, and of it require an account: and what euill counſell ye haue taken in the day time, either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſing deceit, or circumuenting your neighbour, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of any corrupt luſts; thoſe, when ye haue produced and broughs them forth, — and haue ſet your conſcience as the Iudge to theſe wicked thoughts, ſtrike them thorow, and
<note n="g" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chryſoſt. Exp. in Pſ. 4. pag. 26, C.</note> take reuenge vpon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. The ſecond inducement, is the practice of good men, mingled with their exhortations and encouragements to this worke. In which kinde, and for which purpoſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We firſt reade in Scriptures, of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he practiſed himſelfe, what he preached to others. He that ſaid vnto others, <hi>Commune with your own heart, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith of himſelfe,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 77.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I call to remembrance my ſong in the night; I commune with mine owne heart, and my ſpirit made diligent ſearch.</hi> And in another place,
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.59.</note> 
                  <hi>I thought on my waies,</hi> (ſaith hee)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12751:9"/>
                  <hi>and turned my feete vnto thy teſtimonies.</hi> In which words we may by the way note two things: Firſt, the acts that <hi>Dauid</hi> did doe, and they were, hee thought on [or conſidered] his waies, and hee turned his feete vnto Gods Commandements, <hi>.i.</hi> he did goe on in the way of Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, doing what God did command him. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we may note the order that <hi>Dauid</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the doing of theſe acts, and that was, hee firſt thought on his own waies, and then he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on in Gods Lawes: that is, firſt hee <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and then he reformed his life. And heerein he hath left vs a paterne for our practice, that if we meane to amend our liues, wee alſo muſt firſt begin with the examination of our waies. And the like both practice and paterne wee haue in the afflicted Church in the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie.</hi> For there the Church, taught by the Prophet, thus encourageth each other,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lam. 3.40.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs ſearch</hi> (ſay they) <hi>and try our waies, and turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the Lord:</hi> implying, that examination is the ready way to conuerſion and amendment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We reade in the writings of the Ancients, that religious people haue beene accuſtomed to keepe a day-booke of their actions, and out of that to take an account of their life.
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad cuius la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſum cingulo breuem libellum conſpicerem, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> eum quotidie cogitationes ſuas in eo notare, baſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, omnes nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiare Paſtori ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> Climac. Gradu. 4. extat tom. 6. part. 2. Biblioth. Patr. pag. 251.</note> 
                  <hi>Climacus</hi> telleth, that in a religious houſe, whereinto he came, he <hi>found one, who had a little booke tyed at his girdle, in which he wrote all his thoughts; that keeping a memoriall of them, he might</hi> (beſides his owne care) <hi>ſhew them to his ſpirituall Father.
<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Non ſolum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem illum, ſed et alios quàm plures id facere ibidem proſpexi.</hi> Clima, ibid.</note> Nor was it this man alone that did vſe this courſe, but I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12751:9"/>found</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>very many others to doe the like.</hi> And in the proceſſe of the ſame diſcourſe, he aduiſeth men who are carefull of their ſaluation, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the like order, telling vs,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Optimus ille Trapczita eſt, qui quotidie veſpere lucrum ac detrimentum omnino co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>putat. Qund ſcire mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtius non poteſt, niſi horis ſinguli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in tabulis omnia denotet.</hi> Clima. ibid. pa. 255. B.</note> 
                  <hi>that he is the beſt Banker or Tradeſman, that euery day in the euening taketha perfect account of his gaines and his loſſes. Which a man can no way know better, then if euery houre he note all things downe in his tables.</hi> And to like purpoſe,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Chr. in Pſ. 4. pa. 26. &amp; in Mat. Hom. 43. [pag. 397, 398.] prope finem.</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Serm. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitor. de Abdicatione rerum, in fine. pag. 246. B. &amp; de Inſtit. Mon. in fine. pa. 396. C.</note> S. <hi>Baſil,</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Moral. lib. 25. cap. 6.</note> S. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">De vita ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litar. ad fratres de Monte Dei. pag 1026, &amp; 1029.</note> S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and others moe of thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Worthies, doe aduiſe and encourage religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chriſtians of their time, to a daily examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their conſciences, that in the morning they ſhould thinke how they haue paſſed the night, and in the euening, how they haue ſpent the day. And this daily care, and continuall accounting with their ſoules, was (as wee may well ſuppoſe) one chiefe reaſon, why thoſe times did ſo farre out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe and exceede ours in zeale and deuotion. But certaine it is, that the practice of this exerciſe in thoſe daies, was very frequent and vſuall with all them that made any profeſſion of Religion; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as that
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Debet</hi> [<hi>vniuſcuiuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, mens</hi>] <hi>caute penfare, vel quae ab eo</hi> [<hi>Domino</hi>] <hi>bona perceperit, vel quae mala bonis illius peruersè viuendo reſponderit. Quod electi quotidie facere non ceſſant. Et paulo poſt, Reproborum eſſe proprium ſolei, ſemper praue agere, et nunquam quae egerint, retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare.— At contrà electorum eſt, actas ſuos quotidie ab ipſo cogitationis fonte diſcutere, et om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e quod turbidum profluit, ab intimis exſiccare.</hi> Gregor. Moral. lib. 25. cap. 6.</note> S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Elect do by no meanes ceaſe euery day heedfully to weigh, either what good things they haue receiued from God, or what euill things they haue returned him for his good, by their naughty liuing.</hi> He addeth further, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12751:10"/>
                  <hi>it is vſually a property of reprobates, alwaies to doe euill, and neuer to recount what they haue done:—and contrariewiſe, that it is the property of the Elect to diſcuſſe their deedes euery day from the very thought, which is the ſpring of all; and whatſoeuer they finde to be myrie or muddy, to dry that vp to the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</hi> And hereby we may ſee what the practice &amp; opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ancient Doctors of the Church, and other religious men of thoſe daies was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this dutie of Examination. I proceede further to conſider what wiſe and vertuous men among the Heathen haue thought and ſaid of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly then, we may reade in good Authors among the Heathens, that their beſt and wiſeſt men were woont euery day to take an account of themſelues. <hi>Sextius</hi> the Romane Philoſopher
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Faciebat hoc Sextius, vt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummato die quum ſe ad noc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnam quietem recepiſſet, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogaret animum ſuum,</hi> Quod hodie malum tuum ſanaſti? Cui vitio ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiſti? Qua parte mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es? Senec. de Ira. l. 3. cap 36. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>98. Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald de Hiſtor. Poetarum, Dialog. 4. pag 156.</note> 
                  <hi>had this cuſtome, that at the end of the day, when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke himſelfe to his nights reſt, hee would queſtion his ſoule, What maladie of thine haſt thou this day cured? What vice haſt thou ſtood out againſt? In what reſpect art thou better then thou waſt before?</hi> And <hi>Seneca,</hi> who reporteth this of <hi>Sextius,</hi> did practiſe the like himſelfe.
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quotidie apud me cauſam dico. Quum ſublatum e conſpectu lume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, et conticuit vxer, moris iam mei conſcia, totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diem mecum ſcrutor, facta ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicta mea reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior. Nihil mihi ipſe abſcondo, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil tranſco. Quare enim quicquam ex er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roribus meis ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meam, quum poſſum dicere; Vide ne iſtuc amplius facias, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unc tibi ignoſco.</hi> Senec. de Ira, l. 3. c. 36. pag. 199.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery day</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I pleade my cauſe with my ſelfe. When the candle is remoued from mine eyes, and my wife, who is priuy to my cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, keepeth ſilence, I examine the whole day with my ſelfe, I goe ouer againe, and weigh my deedes and my words. I hide nothing from my ſelfe, I paſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ouer vntouched. For what need I to bee afraid of my ſcapes, ſeeing I may ſay to my ſelfe; See thou doe it no more hereafter; for this time I forgiue thee, &amp;c.</hi> The like was the practice of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12751:10"/>ſcholars,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fer tur diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pules admonere ſolitus, vt iſta quotidie quum domum ingrede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, dicerent,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Diogen. Laert, in vita Pythagorae, pa. 581.</note> 
                  <hi>who had this rule giuen them from their Maſter, that enery day when they came home, they ſhould demand each man of himſelfe, Wherein haue I tranſgreſsed? What good haue I done? and what duty haue I left vndone?</hi> And
<note n="(b)" place="margin">De Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate. p. 515. f.</note> 
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth the ſame rule to them that would buſie themſelues in that which may auaile them. Nor was the cuſtome of <hi>Plato</hi> much different from this practice,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plato, quoties interfuiſſet homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus contra de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum agentibus, digreſſus ſolebat it a ſeipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alloqui;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Plut. de vtilit. capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. ex hoſtib. pag. 88. D.</note> 
                  <hi>who, as often as hee was among men that miſ-behaued themſelues, was accuſtomed in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate to queſtion with himſelfe, AND AM NOT I SVCH A ONE?</hi> or, Haue not I done the like? And in a word, ſo generall and common is this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice among all men, to examine or take accounts of their ſtate in all buſineſſes of moment, whether temporall or ſpirituall, as that our Sauiour asketh of the multitudes about him;
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Luk. 14.28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Which of you inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to build a Towre, ſitteth not downe firſt &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the coſt, whether he haue ſufficient to finiſh it &amp;c. or what King going to make warre againſt another King, ſitteth not downe firſt &amp; conſulteth whether he bee able with ten thouſand to meete him that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth againſt him with twenty thouſand? Or elſe, while the other is yet a great way off, hee ſendeth an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, and deſireth conditions of peace.</hi> He meaneth, that there is no man of any ordinary capacitie and wit, but if he bee to build, will firſt take ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his abilitie to perfect the worke; or if he be to make warre, will firſt take a view of his ſtrength to goe thorow with the victory, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he may prouide that which is ſufficient for the ſucceſſe, or elſe he may leaue off his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12751:11"/>on. And then he applyeth this practice in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the world, to a like care in matters of a mans ſoule; <hi>So</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>whoſoeuer he be of you that forſaketh not all that he hath, he cannot bee my Diſciple.</hi> The meaning is as if he ſhould ſay, So euery one of you, that meaneth to be my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhould firſt ſit you downe, and caſt with your ſelues, what it will coſt you to bee a Chriſtian; and that is the renouncing of all the world, and the forſaking of all that you haue in the world. And therefore you ſhould reſolue in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, either to leaue all, if neede be, for Chriſts ſake, or elſe neuer vndertake to be Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>And theſe things laid together, that al wiſe men, whether Chriſtian or Heathen, haue thought this courſe of Examination to bee neceſſary, both in things of the world, and in things of God; yea, and that our bleſſed Sauiour, and the holy Ghoſt ſpeaking in the Scriptures, haue commended this practice vnto vs: theſe, I ſay, may be ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements to make vs well-affected to the worke, before we know in particular what is required in the vndertaking of it, or what may bee expected by the performing of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12751:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Wherein the performance of this worke doth conſiſt, and what actions or performances it doth require.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing hitherto prepared the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders minde to haue a good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this worke, I now go on to conſider, wherein it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilt. And for conceiuing hereof, we muſt conſider, that Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a kind of judiciary proceeding, in which a man keepeth priuate Seſſions at home, paſſing ſentence of all his workes and actions, as Gods Law doth require. This the Apoſtle implyeth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing firſt ſaid,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe, &amp; ſo let him eate, &amp;c.</hi> he addeth by way of confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to proue the neceſſity or profitablenes of this work,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">verſ. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>For if we would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not be iudged;</hi> that is, if wee would cenſure and paſſe ſentence on our ſelues, by a diligent perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this worke of Examination; God would ſpare vs, or he would not cenſure vs the ſecond time, after we had done it our ſelues already. To this purpoſe
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Expoſit. in Pſal. 4.</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> calleth it <hi>an erecting of a Tribunall for the conſcience;</hi> and S. <hi>Gregorie,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nec deeſt in hoc Iudicio men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te concepto, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne miniſterium, quod punire reo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſuos pleniùs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat. Nam Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia accuſat, Ratio iudicat, Tiraor ligat, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor excruciat.</hi> Greg. Moral. l. 25. cap. 6.</note> that in this priuate iudgèment there wanteth no Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer that is vſuall for puniſhing of guilty perſons: for the Conſcience</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the Accuſer; Reaſon is the Iudge; Feareus the Gaeler, and Sorr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12751:12"/>And therefore looke, what the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, and what actions are vſuall in publike Iudgements, where men are queſtioned and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced according to Law: and the like courſe is heere to bee held, and the ſame actions are to be performed in the examination of a mans ſoule &amp; conſcience. For as in thoſe legall proceedings, there is firſt an enquirie into the facts, what hath beene done, which by the Law deſerueth cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Secondly, there is ſentence pronounced, according to the nature of the crimes, and the proofe made of them. Thirdly, there is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inflicted, either for the amendment of the offender, or for example and terror to others, that they offend not in like ſort. Or, if the partie accuſed be cleared by the Iurie, hee is acquitted and ſet free by the Iudge. So in this Court of priuate Seſſions, firſt, there is an enquirie or ſearch, to finde out the tranſgreſſions or offences of the ſoule. Secondly, there is ſentence to bee pronounced, according as the nature of the facts doth require. Thirdly, if the ſentence bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnatory, puniſhment is to be inflicted by the offenders conſcience vpon himſelfe; that by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a holy reuenge vpon his owne folly, hee may be made more carefull of offending after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Or if a man ſhall be ſo happy, as after enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to find nothing by himſelfe; he may cheere his ſoule with an <hi>Euge ſerue bone &amp;c.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 25.21.</note> Well done thou good and faithfull ſeruant.</hi> And heereby the ſincere Chriſtian may bee encouraged in Gods ſeruice, and animated to proceede in thoſe holy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12751:12"/>courſes, in which hee hath found ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort already. And becauſe there is no man that doth faithfully performe this ſeruice of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his ſoule, but he ſhall be ſure to finde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, wherein hee hath ſinned, and ſomething wherein he hath ſerued God aright; therefore he ſhall neuer want matter either to condemne, or in ſome part to abſolue himſelfe, more or leſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as his life hath beene in times paſt, and according as he hath made vſe of this and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exerciſes of Religion. And conſequently in euery Examination, if it be throughly performed, a man will lightly gaine two helps toward Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Firſt, by condemning of himſelfe, he will conceiue feare of relapſing into ſinne: and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by acquitting himſelfe, hee will gaine more comfort to proceede in well-doing.</p>
               <p>By this it may appeare in part, what the nature of this worke is, and wherein it doth conſiſt: but for the more diſtinct knowledge of this point, it may further be noted, that there be two ſorts of acts which are implyed in this word Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in ſome ſort included in it: ſome are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall, and contained in the nature of it; and ſome are accidentall, and to be conioyned with it, and indeed are preſuppoſed to accompany it, when it is rightly vndertaken.</p>
               <p>Of the former ſort are theſe three, 1 Diſcuſſion, 2 Application, and 3 Cenſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diſcuſsion</hi> is a ſifting of our life and dealings, by which we pull things out of the heape where before they lay confuſed and vnſeene, and by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12751:13"/>which we ſet euery fact of ours in the open view, that they may be ſcanned and ſeene by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues what they are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Application</hi> is a laying of theſe acts thus ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and found out, to the rule of Gods Law, which is the touchſtone of all our doings, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which God will iudge vs at the laſt day: that ſo it may appeare how and wherein we haue ſwarned from Gods Law, or haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>Cenſure</hi> is the iudgement that our mindes and conſciences doe giue vpon our deeds according to the rule of the Law; both for the quality of them, whether they bee righteous or ſinfull; and for the quantity of the offence, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be great or ſmall; whether a ſinne of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or a ſinne againſt conſcience; and whether of humane frailety, or of obdurate contumacie.</p>
               <p>The firſt act ſerueth to ſhew what wee haue done: the ſecond, what wee ſhould haue done: and the third, what the doome is that wee haue deſerued either by well or ill doing. And theſe three laid together, doe (as I take it) make vp the nature of this worke of Examination; ſo that we may not vnfitly deſcribe it out of its owne prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, in ſome ſuch maner as this; Examination is a diſcuſſion of a mans life, that his workes may be ſeene and cenſured according to the rule of Gods Law.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for the ſecond ſort of acts, which are implyed in this word, and ought to be ioyned with this worke, they are two eſpecially, the one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12751:13"/>going before the proper acts of Examination, and that is a purpoſe to better a mans ſpirituall eſtate, by correcting what is amiſſe, and confirming what is ſound and vpright. And the other is an act that followeth after Examination, &amp; that is an effectuall practice or execution of ſuch rules and orders as may back our examination, and make it more effectual &amp; vſefull. For which purpoſe, theſe rules following may perhaps be not impertinent nor vnfit: euery wiſe Chriſtian may, as his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhall giue him further occaſion, adde, and vſe more of his owne or other mens obſeruation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Rule.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>1</label> That after wee haue examined our ſoule,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. de Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione rerum in fine. p. 246.</note> we doe then compare our preſent with our precedent ſtate, and conſider whether we haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended indeed, what we blamed our ſelues for in our former examinations; and how wee haue either increaſed or decreaſed in grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: that if we haue been ſlothfull and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruants, we may ſnubbe and ſhame our ſelues for it before God and our owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in ſome ſuch manner as our Lord ſnubbed the euill ſeruant in the Goſpell,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Matt. 25.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou wicked and ſlothfull ſeruant, &amp;c.</hi> and if wee haue beene dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and in ſome meaſure haue encreaſed our Lords talents, that then wee may cheere our ſoules out of the comfort of our wel-doing, and praiſe our God, that hath both giuen vs talents to trade with, and grace to vſe them to his glory. For this practice will whett our diligence for time to come.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>2</label> That euery morning before wee begin our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12751:14"/>worke, we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what we are going about, what occaſions of doing good either to our ſelues or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we may meete with, and what tentations may aſſault vs in the buſineſſes of that day; that ſo wee may lay hold vpon all occaſions of doing good, and prepare our ſelues to ſtand out with courage againſt all oppoſitions and tentations that may hinder vs in our duties, or draw vs into ſinne. For by this meanes, occaſions of doing well ſhall not ouerſlip vs vn-eſpied, nor will ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſurprize vs at vnawares.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>3</label> That if we haue profited in grace, and haue taken occaſions of doing good, we conſider at fit times, by what meanes wee haue profited and haue beene enabled to doe well; that ſo we may make more conſtant vſe of ſuch meanes, by which we haue found ſo much ſenſible good al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. And if wee haue decayed, or forſlowed our opportunities, or haue runne into any ſinne, then we ſhould obſerue, what it was that did miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leade vs, and by what tentations wee were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, that our former errors may make vs more warie and more reſolute againſt caſes of danger, for the time to come. For by this meanes we ſhall euery day gaine ſome experience, how to behaue our ſelues in the daily conflicts of our Chriſtian warfare.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>4</label> That we recall home our thoughts, as wee meete with any occaſions of moment, or light vpon any ſuch buſineſſe, as concerning which we haue formerly conceiued a purpoſe of warie and religious behauiour: that while we are in doing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12751:14"/>of the worke, we may remember to make vſe of our former reſolution, and now practiſe what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we did purpoſe. For by this meanes wee ſhall be ſure that our good purpoſes ſhall not bee idle and without fruite; as in many men it falleth out, who are like ſluggiſh people, that ouer-night ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point to riſe early, but when the morning com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, cannot abide to leaue their warme beds.</p>
               <p>Theſe Rules I haue thought on, as beeing in mine opinion fit to backe our examination, and to make it more powerfull for an holy life: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as I ſaid before, may in their daily obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion adde moe, and perhaps finde out ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then theſe. And as in the ordering of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily health, Phyſicians aduiſe their Patients to follow that whereof they finde good, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd that which doth not agree with their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: ſo it is good counſell in the ordering of our ſoules, to make daily vſe of that which by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience wee finde either to ſtrengthen grace, or to weaken ſinne in vs: and contrariwiſe to flee from all ſuch occaſions and vſages, as wee ſee or haue found to hurt or endanger vs. I onely adde thus much more; That theſe later ſort of acts, whereof now I haue beene ſpeaking, though in themſelues ſimply conſidered they bee but Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts and Attendants on Examination, without which it may ſubſiſt in its bare nature; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not neceſſary <hi>ad eſse;</hi> as the Schooles doe ſpeake: yet in the vſe of the word, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment of the Scripture they are implyed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and preſuppoſed to goe with it and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12751:15"/>it, as being neceſſary <hi>ad bene eſse,</hi> to the well doing of this worke: as may appeare by theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> It is the vſe and cuſtome of Scripture, vnder words of knowledge belonging to the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to comprehend affections and practice. As when Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> faith,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that ſaith I knowe God, and keepeth not his Commandements, is a lyer, and the truth is not in him:</hi> hee meaneth not by the word <hi>[know]</hi> a bare and ſimple knowing and apprehending, which the learned call <hi>cognitio ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſina;</hi> but he meaneth an effectuall and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king knowledge, which breedeth or bringeth forth ſuch affections in the heart and ſuch actions in the life, as that knowledge directeth men to: which knowledge they call <hi>[cognitio affectiua.]</hi> And ſo in this caſe, Examination is properly a worke of the vnderſtanding, fingling things out of the confuſed heape, that they may appeare what they are: but by way of conſequent it doth imply ſuch affections and actions, as this worke of the vnderſtanding is intended for, which is the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and a heading of our ſpirituall eſtates, and of ordering euery thing for the beſt aduantage of our ſoules and ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ations.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Secondly, that thus much is implyed and intended by this word, may hereby appeare, that the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the danger of vnworthy receiving of the Lords Supper, and preſcribing meanes to correct all abuſe that way,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23.</note> ſaith; <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this Bread, and drinke of this Cup.</hi> For if by the vvord
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12751:15"/>
                  <hi>[examine]</hi> he meant nothing but <hi>diſcuſsing</hi> and ſifting without <hi>correcting</hi> and amending; hee ſhould allow men to go to the Communion with the conſcience of ſinne, and without reformation of life. And which is yet worſe, ſhould approue of a man as a worthy gueſt at the Lords Table, onely becauſe he hath learned to know his eſtate, though he no way meane to amend it; whereas this knowledge of a mans ſelfe would increaſe his ſinne, and make him the leſſe welcome vnto God; according to that rule of our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.47.</note> 
                  <hi>That ſeruant which knew his Lords will, and prepared not himſelfe, neither did according to his will, ſhall bee beaten with many ſtripes. But he that knew not, and did commit things worthy of ſtripes, ſhall bee beaten with few ſtripes.</hi> And therefore when the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let a man examine, and ſo let him eate, &amp;c.</hi> hee meaneth, that after hee hath examined, hee ſhould amend whatſoeuer is amiſſe, and perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e whatſoeuer vpon examination he ſhall finds, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary or fit to bee done. And hence it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that a purpoſe to amend our life, and to doe what vpon our examining ſhall appeare neceſſary for our ſoules, is a neceſſary duty, as an antecedent act that ſhould goe before Examination; and that a practice of ſuch things, as by tryall ſhall appeare vſefull for this purpoſe, is another neceſſary duty, as a conſequent act that ſhould follow after it. And ſo in concluſion it appeareth that there are three eſpeciall acts required for the right perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this worke: 1, a conſtant reſolution to amend and better the eſtate of the ſoule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12751:16"/>ſearch, thereby to gaine the right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it: and 3, an effectuall performance of all ſuch things, as are auaileable for this purpoſe. And out of all theſe laid together, we may make a more full deſcription to this purpoſe; Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is a Diſcuſſion of a mans life, for finding out the true eſtate of a mans ſoule toward God; accompanied with a purpoſe and endeuour to doe whatſoeuer vpon tryall ſhall appeare requiſite for ſaluation and the good of a mans ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Obiect of this worke, or the matter about which it is to be exerciſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto we haue ſpoken of the acts, now we are to conſider of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, or matter about which they are to be beſtowed and imployed. And it may bee conſidered two wayes; either generally and ſuch as it is in the largeſt extent, which wee may call the <hi>adequate</hi> obiect; or ſpecially, and ſuch as is in more prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall manner to bee reſpected and looked to, which may be called the <hi>Principall</hi> or ſpeciall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
               <p n="1">I. And firſt for the <hi>adequate</hi> obiect, including euery thing that ought to be examined, or about which a Chriſtian ſhould examine himſelfe; it is whatſoeuer either thought word or deede, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12751:16"/>carrieth any reſpect either of righteouſnes or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in it, or all both our good and our euill deedes. For Examination being (as before was noted) a kinde of iudiciary proceeding with our owne ſoules, in which wee keepe Seſſions at home, that we may prepare for the great Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: it hath for its obiect the ſame matter, that ſhall be diſcuſſed and ſentenced at the day of the laſt Iudgement. And that is, (as <hi>Solomon</hi> telleth vs) <hi>euery worke whether good or euill. For
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eccles. 11.14.</note> GOD</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall bring euery worke into iudgement, with euery ſecret thing, whether it bee good or euill:</hi> that is, euery thing that is morally euill or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally good, or which is either ſinfull or righteous. And therefore in imitation of Gods proceeding in his Iudgement, we alſo ſhould proceede in our iudging of our ſelues; which is to conſider of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing, which is either good or euill, ſinfull or righteous, a breach of Gods Law or a perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it.</p>
               <p>But for our more diſtinct vnderſtanding, and our better direction heerein, it will not bee amiſſe to conſider our good and our euill workes, each a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part by themſelues.</p>
               <p>And firſt for our euill deedes or our ſinnes, wee may note theſe rules following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt conſider and examine our ſchies, as well concerning our omiſſions of duties, as commiſſions of euils. For in the laſt Iudgement, our Lord the Iudge of quicke and dead, he will not onely giue ſentence againſt murders and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and robberies, and ſuch like, but
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Matth. 25.41, 42, 43.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12751:17"/>vnmercifulneſſe alſo, and the not <hi>feeding of the hungry,</hi> the <hi>not lodging of the ſtranger,</hi> the <hi>not clothing of the naked,</hi> the <hi>not viſiting of the ſicke, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo when wee are to iudge our ſelues, wee muſt cenſure not onely our hurting of our neighbour, but our not helping of him; nor one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our back-biting of our neighbour, but our not defending of his good name; nor onely our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting of Gods Word, but our not profiting by it; nor onely our robbing of the poore, but our not relieuing of them: and ſo in all other the like caſes, our not doing of that which is good, when dutie doth require it of vs, is culpable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and is part of that matter about which our Examination ought to be exerciſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt conſider not onely the ſubſtance of our ſinnes, but the circumſtances of them alſo; ſuch as are the perſons, the time, the place, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion or manner of doing, &amp;c. for all theſe may either aggrauate or mitigate the ſinne. So we ſee that the treaſon of <hi>Iudas</hi> is counted the more grieuous,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.9. &amp; Ioh. 13.18.</note> becauſe he was one of Chriſts <hi>familiar friends, which did cate of his bread;</hi> and <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſses</hi> his idolatrie was the more hainous, becauſe hee
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Chron. 33.7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſet his idol in the Houſe of God, of which GOD had ſaid to Dauid, and to Solomon his Sonne; In this Houſe and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eruſalem which I haue choſen before all the tribes of Iſrael, will I put my name for euer.</hi> And ſo, the cruel dealing of the Iews was the more hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, becauſe
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 58.3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>in the day of their faſt, they did exact all their labours,</hi> and <hi>did ſmite with the fiſt of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.</hi> And <hi>Solomons</hi> idolatry did anger &amp; offend
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12751:17"/>God the more, becauſe
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 King. 11.9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>his heart was turned from the Lord, which had appeared vnto him twiſe, and had commanded him concerning this thing, that hee ſhould not goe after other Gods.</hi> And ſo our ſinnes will be the more grieuous, if we wrong them who haue helped vs, or if in the Church of God, and in the time of his ſeruice, our hearts doe meditate reuenge, or forecaſt vniuſt deuices, or take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to thinke on our fleſhly luſts, &amp;c. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe circumſtances are to come into the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count together with the maine ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, not onely the ſinne, but the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it is to be conſidered: for this may either increaſe or diminiſh the guiltineſſe of it. As the rich man that had many ſheepe of his owne, and yet tooke away <hi>the poore mans lambe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.1. &amp;c.</note> to make his friend welcome with, was the more grieuous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender by much, becauſe hauing no neede, hee did rob the poore man. And again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the occaſion or prouocation by which we were led into ſinne, may teach vs wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, by ſhunning ſuch occaſions to eſcape from the ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, wee are to reckon among our ſins, that muſt be accounted for, not onely our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of euill deedes, and omiſſions of good duties, but euen our vnperfect and defectiue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances. For of theſe the Church of God doth accuſe themſelues;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 64.6.</note> 
                  <hi>All our righteouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are as filthy raggs:</hi> and in reſpect of theſe it was, that the High Prieſt was by the Law
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Exod. 28.38.</note> to <hi>carrie the iniquity of the holy things, which the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12751:18"/>of Iſrael ſhould hallow, in all their holy gifts:</hi> For that doth imply, that the ſeruices of Gods people had their imperfections and errors, which becauſe they were failings in duties, were to bee borne by Ieſus our High Prieſt, as our other ſins were. And therefore wee muſt reckon with our ſelues not onely for omitting or neglecting the exerciſes of Religion, but for our diſtractions, our wandring thoughts, and our cold and dull affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, while we did performe them.</p>
               <p>Thus our euill deedes or ſinnes may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: our good workes and holy duties may not be neglected neither; and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe we are many times deceiued with ſhewes; thinking that to be good which is euill, and that to bee ſome great good, which is but a poore ſeruice in compariſon. Thus
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Philip. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> thought hee ſhewed much <hi>zeale,</hi> when <hi>bee perſecuted the Church of Chriſt:</hi> and
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iudg. 17.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Micah</hi> thought hee had highly demerited Gods fauour, when hee kept a Prieſt for idolatrous ſeruice: and <hi>Iehu</hi> boaſted of his killing of <hi>Ahabs</hi> children;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 King. 10.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Come with me,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſee my zeale for the Lord:</hi> when as God cenſured it for vniuſt ſhedding of blood;
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Hoſ. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Yet a little while</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and I will auenge the blood of Iezreel vpon the houſe of Iehu.</hi> And ſo wee are too apt to ouerweene our ſelues and our owne workes; and thinke that we are zealous for God, when we are enuious againſt men, or ambitious for our ſelues. And for diſcerning of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, examination is neceſſary to bee vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe workes which wee eſteeme to bee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12751:18"/>righteous and holy, leſt wee deceiue our ſelues by ouer-partiall iudgement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe in the very workes which are truly good, wee doe many times intermingle corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our owne: As ſometimes there are ill ends in our good deedes, as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 King. 21.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Iezebel</hi> proclaimed a faſt to cloke her murder withall, and
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 6.2, 5, 16.</note> the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes faſted and prayed and gaue almes, for gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vaine praiſes. And ſometimes our good duties are performed in an euill manner; as the
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Exod. 1.17, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Midwiues</hi> ſaued the childrens liues, by telling of a lye; and
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Exod. 4.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Zipporah</hi> circumciſed her ſonne, in a pettiſh humour; and
<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Chron. 13.9. compared with cap. 15.12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Vzzah</hi> ſtayed the Arke from falling, without ſufficient warrant for ſuch a worke. But moſt times there are diſtractions, and worldly or perhaps wicked thoughts in the midſt of our beſt deuotions: and alwayes there are defects and imperfections and failings when we are moſt feruent and beſt affected. And for diſcerning of theſe, our beſt workes deſerue a ſtrict account, that we may learne to ſeparate the <hi>precious from the vile:</hi> and neither be too highly conceited of our weake performances, nor too little affected with our corruptions and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our good workes are to bee conſidered in our Examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that by thoſe things which are able to abide the touchſtone, we may gaine cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage againſt oppoſitions of men, and comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tentations of Satan, and a ſettled re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to proceede and goe on in a daily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of good workes; alwaies praiſing God for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12751:19"/>theſe mercies; becauſe it is hee that worketh in vs both the will and the deede. And in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, the conſideration of our good workes is not without good vſe. And this may ſuffice for the <hi>adequate</hi> obiect, or the matter of Examination in generall and in the largeneſſe of it.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Secondly for the principall Obiect, or the ſpeciall matter which is to come into Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is euery ſuch ſinne as is likely to breede vs ſome eſpeciall danger. For if a Citie be beſieged, wiſe <hi>Gouernours</hi> will take care of euery poſterne doore, and of euery part of the Walls, to repaire what is decayed, and to keepe all ſafe from the Enemie: but if one Gate be more likely to bee entred than other, or if any part of the Wall be weaker or more eaſily to be broken downe, men will there ſet the watch the ſureſt, where the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is the greateſt. And if a man be diſtempered with ſundry diſeaſes, a wiſe <hi>Phyſician</hi> will take care of all, to eaſe the Patient, as much as may be, of euery one of them: but if ſome ſpeciall diſeaſe be more dangerous to the ſicke man, than others are; the Phyſician will bend his cure that way e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, where the life of his Patient is moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered. And ſo it is, or ſhould be with vs in reſpect of our ſoules: Wee haue heere a Fort to keepe, which is euery day aſſaulted by our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and we haue a diſeaſed foule of our owne, diſtempered with many ſpirituall maladies: but ſome maladies are worſe then other; and ſome parts of this Fort are weaker or more in danger then others are: I meane, there are ſome ſinnes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12751:19"/>by which the Diuell may more eaſily ſurprize and captiuate our ſoules. And therefore, as wee ſhould keepe diligent watch againſt them all; ſo wee ſhould eſpecially bend our forces againſt thoſe that doe or may more eſpecially breede vs harme, and hinder our ſaluation. And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, Examination being an approued means for grubbing vp of ſinne, wee ſhould apply this exerciſe againſt all ſinnes in generall; but more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially againſt thoſe, from which wee may in reaſon feare the greateſt danger. And theſe are either ſuch ſinnes as are <hi>eaſily contracted,</hi> or ſuch as are <hi>hardly recouered.</hi> For into the one ſort men fall often, and out of other they doe ſeldomer recouer, if they once fall into them: and ſo the one ſort will endanger vs by the <hi>frequencie</hi> of our falls, and the other by the <hi>difficultie</hi> of our riſing after wee bee downe. But for better and more diſtinct vnderſtanding of this point, wee may in a more particular manner conſider the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſorts of ſinne, which in either of theſe two reſpects may breede ſome eſpeciall danger. And of this kinde I take theſe ſinnes following to bee.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe that be great and <hi>reigning</hi> ſins: ſuch as the Apoſtle ſaith doe exclude a man out of Gods Kingdome. And in this kind he reckoneth,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9. Galat. 5.19, 20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, idolatrie, adultery, effeminateneſse, ſodomie, theft, couetouſnes, drunkennes, reuilings, extortion.</hi> Of which ſinnes, and ſuch like, he ſaith, that they that are guilty of them, <hi>ſhall not inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> And he meaneth, that while they are ſuch, or till by repentance and forſaking of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12751:20"/>them, they haue obtained pardon, they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come into Gods Kingdome. Againſt theſe <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Keepe backe thy ſeruant from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſins, let them not haue dominion ouer me: then ſhall I be vpright, and I ſhall bee innocent from the great tranſgreſsion.</hi> And againſt theſe wee ſhould watch and pray, that we may auoyd them; or if we haue falne into them, wee ſhould by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination learne to conceiue the danger, that by repentance we may gaine pardon. For whereas leſſer ſinnes, ſuch as <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 19.12.</note> 
                  <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret faults, .i.</hi> ſinnes, which in regard of their fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and our frailety, doe eſcape vs through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, vnwarines, or common and humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie;
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.8.</note> whereas, I ſay, theſe ſins are in the beſt of Gods children; (for euen they ſay, <hi>If we ſay that we haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs:</hi>) one of theſe other groſſe ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as cannot be committed, but with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and purpoſe of ſinne in the offender, doth bereaue men for the preſent of grace, and all title and intereſt to the Kingdome of Heauen. And therefore we ſhould haue an eſpeciall care to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our ſoules concerning theſe groſſer ſinnes, that we doe not ſuffer our ſelues to liue and lye in any of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sinnes of <hi>recidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation</hi> and relapſe, when we fall backe into the former ſinne, after our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and vowes of a better life. For relapſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſickneſſe are dangerous for the body; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes into ſinne are no leſſe dangerous for the ſoule. And therefore our Sauiour ſaid to the man
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12751:20"/>whom hee had cured of his lameneſſe,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Sinne no more, leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee:</hi> and that if the <hi>vncleane ſpirit,</hi> which hath beene caſt out of a man,
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.24.</note> 
                  <hi>doe returne and finde the houſe ſwept and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,</hi> that is, made fit for the habitation of ſuch a gueſt, <hi>then he goeth and taketh with him ſeuen other ſpirits more wicked then himſelfe, and they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in and dwell there; and the laſt ſtate of that man is worſe then the firſt.</hi> By this it appeareth, that theſe kind of ſinnes, into which wee haue falne before, if after our recouerio we relapſe into them againe, are moſt dangerous and preiudiciall to a mans ſoule. And therefore when wee call our ſoules to account, wee ſhould more eſpecially examine them concerning the former ſins which we committed before time; that wee may ſee how well or how ill wee haue continued the courſe of our repentance and amendment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sinnes that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e with our owne <hi>diſpoſitions,</hi> ſuch, I meane, as wee are inclined vnto, either through temper of nature or cuſtome of life. For theſe ſinnes may breede ſpeciall danger, becauſe we are ready to drop into them, when no other Tempter driueth vs, beſide our owne corruption. Of ſuch <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeemeth to ſpeake, when he ſaith; <hi>I kept my ſelfe from mine iniquitie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.23.</note> And of ſuch we alſo ſhould beware. And therefore in the daily care of our ſoules, we ſhould more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally queſtion and examine them concerning thoſe ſinnes, to which we are addicted or diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, either by nature or by cuſtome.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſinnes of each mans particular <hi>calling</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12751:21"/>or <hi>trade,</hi> may eſpecially endanger him, becauſe he hath by his very courſe of life, ſo many and ſo vſuall occaſions to be tempted by them. Neuer a day, nor ſcarce an houre of a day, but ſome bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe will come in his way, either in dealing with others, or in deliberating by himſelfe, by which he may be occaſioned either to omit ſome dutie, or to doe ſome wrong, or to follow ſome neerer way of thriuing than GOD doth allow him. And amidſt ſo many and frequent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it will bee hard to ſtand vpright, without much care and watchfulnes. And therefore as S. <hi>Paul</hi> preſcribeth vnto ſeueral men, the duties that belong to their ſeuerall ſtates and conditions; as to him <hi>that hath</hi> the gift of <hi>prophecie,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> that hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie according to the proportion of faith;</hi> and to him <hi>that hath an office, that he waite vpon his office;</hi> and ſo he <hi>that teacheth, on teaching, &amp;c:</hi> ſo, if we deſire to looke into the ſtate of our ſoules, and to learne from our owne hearts, how well or how ill we haue done our duties, we ſhould haue an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall eye to ſuch things as appertaine to our particular places and callings.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The ſinnes of the <hi>time, place,</hi> and <hi>companie</hi> in which we liue, haue ſpeciall danger in them. For firſt they will draw vs by their very exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to partake with them; in ſo much, as that men who at the beginning doe abhorre them, yet by continuance of time, are inſenſibly carried with them, before themſelues can tell how. And ſecondly, euill men doe deſire companie in their ſinne, and doe vſually ſtriue by all perſwaſions to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12751:21"/>winne ouer to their ſide thoſe that are better af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. And therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith;
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Prou. 1.10, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſonne, if ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not. If they ſay, Come with vs, let vs lay waite for blood,  we ſhall finde all precious ſubſtance, wee ſhall fill our houſes with ſpoile; caſt in thy lot among vs, let vs all haue one purſe: My ſonne, walke not thou in the way with them, &amp;c.</hi> In which words, <hi>Solomon</hi> firſt ſuppoſeth that ſinners will entice, and vſe all plauſible allurements to perſwade others to their ſociety; and then hee aduiſeth the righteous to take heede of them and their ſugred baites. And ſo, if we liue amongſt ſuch men, we muſt expect prouocation from them; and therefore ſhould vſe all prouidence for freeing of our ſelues of them. Thirdly, wicked men, if they cannot win others to take part with them, yet they will mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt them, becauſe their contrarie life is an open ſhame to theſe mens dealings. And therefore the Wiſe man bringeth in the wicked, thus deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berating or rather reſoluing with themſelues;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Wiſd. 2.12, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs lye in waite for the righteous, becauſe he is not for our turne, and he is cleane contrary to our doings: be vpbraideth vs with our offeding the Law, &amp; obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth to our infamie the tranſgreſsings of our educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.—He was made to reproue our thoughts: he is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous to vs, euen to behold: for his life is not like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens, his waies are of another facion. &amp;c.</hi> And this daily molt ſtation from the wicked, will make good men afraid to doe well, for feare of giuing offence, or incurring danger: which made <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſay, that
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>the rod of the wicked ſhould not reſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12751:22"/>the lot of the righteous: leſt the righteous put forth their hands vnto iniquitie:</hi> implying, that if the wicked were ſuffered ſtill to ſcourge &amp; moleſt Gods people, it might be a meanes to make them forſake their integrity, either by ſeeking to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the wicked, or to protect themſelues. By theſe conſiderations it appeareth, that in the company of euill men are many prouocations to ſinne, partly by their bare example, partly by their euill counſell, and moſt of all by deriſion and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or by oppreſſion and iniuries. In reſpect whereof we may ſay, as S.
<note n="*" place="margin">Hieron. in lib. 2. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos Proaem. ad Pammach.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> out of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, [Nullus diu tutus periculo proximus;] No man can be long ſafe, that is alwaies in danger.</hi> And therefore ſuch ſinnes doe require ſpeciall care and watchfulneſſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like ſinnes as theſe, becauſe they breede the greateſt danger, are to bee ſifted and cenſured with the greateſt care. And ſo wee ſee that wiſe men haue held the like courſe in matters of this life, and haue found good ſucceſſe by it. When the King of <hi>Syria</hi> was to ſight with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hee commanded his Captaines,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 King. 22.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Fight neither with ſmall nor great, ſaue onely with the King of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> And the euent ſheweth that the courſe was good: for when the King was ſlaine,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ver. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation then went throughout the Hoſt, Euerie man to his Citie, and euery man to his own Countrie.</hi> And in like ſort <hi>Ageſilaus</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>In pugna ad Mantinéam bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus eſt Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monios, vt omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis reliquis, in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pugnarent Epaminondam; ſolos inquiens prudentes eſſe fortes, et illo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato, facilem fore de reliquis victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam: id quod etiam euenit.</hi> Plut. Apophth. in Ageſil. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>4. C.</note> gaue aduice to the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> in a certaine battell againſt the <hi>Thebans,</hi> that <hi>they ſhould omit all others, and fight onely againſt Epaminondas,</hi> who was the Leader of the Field
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12751:22"/>and a man of as great wiſdome as courage: and he gaue this reaſon for it, <hi>becauſe he being killed, it would be eaſie to conquer all the reſt: which</hi> (as my Author ſaith) <hi>fell out accordingly.</hi> And ſo, vvhen <hi>Goliath</hi> was ſlaine,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.51.</note> 
                  <hi>the Philiſtines ſeeing that their Champion was dead, fled</hi> before <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And ſo in like manner in our conflicts with ſinne, it will be good counſell, that ſometimes omitting all other vices, we bend our ſelues wholly againſt that ſin which troubleth vs moſt: becauſe, if once wee haue quelled our maſter-ſinnes, the Deuils great Leaders and Champions, it will be the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to chaſe away the reſt. And for this cauſe, in the performance of this worke of Examination, a ſpeciall care muſt bee had againſt theſe great Commanders, that they ſcape not away in the throng.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of the maner to be obſerued in this worke, or how a Chriſtian ſhould proceede in examining of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He matter being declared, the next thing to be conſidered, is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: for direction wherein, two things are in the beginning to bee noted:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That in all workes of this kinde,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>1</label> the maner is much-what to be regulated by the matter and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12751:23"/>the end. For Examination, in what kind ſoeuer it be, being a ſearching or enquirie after ſomething that we deſire to know, is alwaies to be ſo perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as may beſt ſerue for the bolting out of that truth which we ſearch for. And as the matter, whereof the queſtion is, and the end for vvhich the enquirie is made, and the diſcouerie which is deſired in this worke, doe differ and diſagree; ſo the manner of proceeding in making the ſearch, will be different and vnlike it ſelfe, as the things whereto it is applyed doe require. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if the Goldſmith be to try his metall, hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the touchſtone and the fornace; becauſe theſe are the proper meanes which his arte doth teach for finding out that which hee deſireth to know. And if the Carpenter be to try his worke that he hath framed, whether it be agreeable to arte, &amp; fit for vſe, he vſeth his ſquire and line and compaſſe; becauſe they beeing applyed to his worke, will ſhew how well it is fitted for the purpoſe. And ſo in like maner, if a Phyſician be to try the ſtate of his Patient, hee looketh vpon the vrine, feeleth the pulſe, and obſerueth the ſymptomes. And if a Iudge be to examine a ſuſpected perſon, he que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioneth him about circumſtances, and examineth him vpon ſuch interrogatories, as may entangle any man, that meaneth by glozing ſhifts to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the truth. Thus in examinations, men fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that courſe which is ſuteable to the matter, and peculiar for that end whereto it is referred.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Examination,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>2</label> as heere it is intended, being a <hi>diſcuſsion</hi> of a mans life, for diſcerning his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12751:23"/>ſpirituall ſtate, is a kind of <hi>indiciarie</hi> proceeding, as hath beene ſhewed
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note> alreadie. And therefore looke what courſe Iudges doe hold in their Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or at their Aſſiſes, the like courſe will be fit to be held in this worke. Now in their Seſſions, this is the courſe: They firſt enquire into the facts of men, and that enquirie is made by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of witneſſes, and other proofes that may ſhew what their deedes haue been: and ſecondly, when they haue found out the truth of the fact, then they goe to the rule of the Law, and that beeing laid to the fact, directeth the Iudge to giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence according vnto right. And ſo in theſe Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions kept in the conſcience, and held for the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of our ſoules, we haue two things to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after; the one what our actions and facts haue beene, ſo farre forth as they concerne our ſpirituall life. And for finding out thereof, our beſt proofe is the teſtimonie of our owne conſcience: which is as good as a thouſand witneſſes, if our ſelues corrupt it not. And the other is, how well theſe actions doe agree with Gods Law, (which is the Law that bindeth the conſcience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the ſoule;) that thence wee may learne what to iudge of our life, how farre forth it agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with Gods Law, or ſwarueth from it.</p>
               <p>Theſe two things being firſt noted in generall; for more particular direction it muſt bee further conſidered, that this comparing of our life with Gods Law, may be done two wayes: wee may either beginne with Gods Law, and firſt ſee what it doth requite at our hands, and thence proceede
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12751:24"/>to our ſelues, and queſtion with our ſoules, how and wherein wee haue obſerued or tranſgreſſed thoſe rules. Or ſecondly, we may beginne with our ſelues, and enquire what our doings are; and then goe to Gods Law, that we may learne what to iudge of ſuch workes.</p>
               <p>If we begin with Gods Law, then we muſt doe two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, wee muſt get a competent knowledge of Gods Law, that wee may know in ſome meaſure what each precept doth require of vs, and what the meaning is of all ſuch Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our practice, the ſumme whereof is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Decalogue or ten Commandements. For as an vnskilfull man is neuer the neerer for a <hi>line</hi> or rule, if he haue not beene taught the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters trade, nor knoweth not the vſe of theſe things; no more can a Chriſtian be any whit the better for hearing or hauing of Gods Law to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him, vnleſſe he know the meaning of it, and can tell what vices are forbidden, and what ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are commanded in euery Precept. Whence it followeth, that they which haue neuer bin train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp in the grounds of Religion, nor haue not the knowledge of their Catechiſme, cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly goe about this ſo neceſſary a worke with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dexterity or profit to their ſoules.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when a man hath learned in ſome good ſort the meaning of the Commandements, then in the ſecond place he is to go through theſe Commandements one by one, and in each of them to conſider what ſinnes are there condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12751:24"/>and what duties are there enioyned, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon ſtill to queſtion with his owne heart, <hi>And haue I committed this ſinne?</hi> or, <hi>Haue I neglected that dutie?</hi> or, <hi>If I haue kept the precept, for the matter, yet haue I not broken it in the maner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, or in the intention of my minde?</hi> And thus wee may proceed, when wee beginne with Gods Law.</p>
               <p>But if we begin firſt with our ſelues, then wee may hold this courſe: firſt, (after ſome compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent knowledge of the Law, which is euer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed in this worke,) we muſt take a view of our life, or of ſo much of it, as then we are occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned and purpoſed to examine, and conſider from time to time, and from one moment to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how we haue beene buſied, in what ſort we behaued our ſelues in it, and what haue beene our deedes, words, and thoughts, that deſerue ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and heereupon ſtill to queſtion with our ſelues, vpon euery worke that admitteth ſuch a queſtion, what therein hath beene done amiſſe, or how we haue tranſgreſſed in the matter, or in the maner, or in the end, or in any circumſtance. In which kinde, that we may proceede the more orderly, and vnderſtand our ſelues and our eſtate the more diſtinctly, we muſt not paſſe ouer things in the groſſe, and lap vp too much of our life in a generall and indiſtinct conſideration; but rather labour to part and diuide our time by ſmaller par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, that ſo we may ſee euery thing apart and by it ſelfe. For which purpoſe, thoſe who haue not better directions already, may be pleaſed to make vſe of theſe.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12751:25"/>
               <p n="1">1. If we be to take a generall account of our whole life, and to examine our ſelues from our beginning to the preſent time; wee may deuide our life ſeuerall wayes. As firſt, by the times of our age, how we were buſied, and in what maner we carried our ſelues towards God, when wee were boyes, and when afterward we were young men, and when men of middle age; and ſo on to our preſent time. Secondly, we may diuide our life by the ſeuerall callings and conditions of life, in which we haue ſpent our time: as what wee did when we were ſcholars at the Grammar ſchoole; what, when we were ſeruants, or Aprentices, or vnder Tutors and Gardians; what, when wee became free-men, or houſeholders, or at our own liberty and diſpoſing; and what in the exerciſing of our particular trade or profeſſion or courſe of life; as Clergie men in their exerciſe of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, Magiſtrates in their places of gouernment, Merchants in their trafficking, Craftſmen in their occupations, and euery man in that vocation whereunto hee is called, and in that profeſſion which he doth exerciſe and beſtowe his life in. Thirdly, we may againe part and (as it were) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuide the time of our ſpeciall Calling, by the ſpeciall buſineſſes which we haue gone thorow, while we haue liued in it; as a Merchant may conſider of his dealing, how iuſt or vniuſt it hath beene in the commodities which he hath carried forth into the Indies, into the Eaſterne Countries, and into other Kingdomes abroad; and how he behaued himſelf in fetching this or that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12751:25"/>from ſuch and ſuch parts, and in venting his wares abroad after they were come home, &amp;c. And ſo may other men doe in the like caſes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the principall buſineſſes and occaſions, that occurre or happen in their ſeueral profeſſions or callings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If we be to conſider of ſome leſſer portion of our life, (as religious men haue beene accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe, by conſidering that time which hath paſſed them ſince their laſt either ordinary or more ſolemne examination,) then wee may part our moneths by weekes, and our weekes by daies, and each day by his ſeuerall houres; that our taske for the preſent being the leſſe, our care and labour about each particular may be the greater.</p>
               <p>Theſe directions for the maner of proceeding, I haue repreſented to ſuch as ſhall vouchſafe to reade this ſchedule; leauing them notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their owne choice, which of theſe wayes they will follow, or whether they will follow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them at all. For thoſe who are accuſtomed to theſe aſceticall exerciſes of deuotion, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps deuiſe other more fitting courſes or wayes of proceeding then theſe are: and it is reaſon, yea and a point of wiſdome too, for euery man to make vſe of thoſe rules, which in his owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience he findeth moſt proper to his own nature, and moſt powerfull for his reformation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. I will only add thus much more for the laſt clauſe of this point; that the more kindes and wayes of proceeding that euery man vſeth, the more knowledge he will gaine of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ne eſtate,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12751:26"/>and the more will he bee enabled to reſiſt ſinne, and to reforme his life and behauiour: for that which eſcapeth him in one maner and courſe of proceeding, may meete him in another; and what one courſe leaueth vnperfect, that the next may ſupply.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the times of Examination, in which it is to bee exerciſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He next thing to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is, what may be the fitteſt times for this exerciſe. And the times to be conſidered are two; When and how often it is to be vſed. For anſwere whereto, the Scriptures, for ought that I know or can obſerue, haue determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned no ſet or preciſe time, which is neceſſary al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be obſerued in the performance of this worke. Notwithſtanding ſome rules there are, partly pointed at in the Scripture, and partly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by holy men, which wee may make vſe of for our good. And they, ſo farre as I can ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and obſerue, be theſe and ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is no danger of ſurfetting vpon too much, nor need we feare leſt we do perform it too often. For firſt, the oftener we reckon with our ſoules, the fewer new things wee ſhall haue at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12751:26"/>time to reckon for; and the fewer the things be, the more readily will they be called to mind, and they may bee ſcanned the more exactly: whereas multitude of things, if they come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will hide one another, and take time one from another, and hinder the notice each of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and ſtill it may be expected, that where many buſineſſes are tumbled in together, ſome will eſcape away in the throng. And ſecondly, the oftener we take account, the freſher will our deedes and actions bee in remembrance; becauſe being lately done, they haue not had ſpace to ſlip out of our mindes. And therefore the oftener the better: nor can there lightly bee any danger in being too diligent. The conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſay of this worke,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Bern. in Cantic. Serm. 58. in fine. pag. 742.</note> 
                  <hi>Si ſemper hoc quum opus eſt, facis, ſemper facis; If ye wil doe this as often as there is neede of it, you must doe it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies.</hi> And it may bee thought, that in reſpect heereof, the Prophet, ſpeaking of this worke, did double his words,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Lam. 3.40.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſearch and try our waies:</hi> implying, that as hee doth double his words, ſo we ſhould double the worke, and after we haue done it once, do it yet ouer againe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The time that learned and deuout men haue been accuſtomed to obſerue, and doe thinke moſt conuenient for an ordinarie practice of this dutie is, that once euery day at leaſt, euery man ſhould conſider of all ſuch things as haue paſſed ſince his laſt reckoning. So ſaith S. <hi>Chryſostom,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoc ſiat ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis diobus: — Et quod facis in pecunia, nee ſinis vt duo dies prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereant, quin cum famulo rationem incas, ne confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem inducat obliuie.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chryſoſt. Exp. in pſal. 4. pag. 27. <hi>A.</hi>
                     </note> Hoc fiat ſingulis diebus; Let this</hi> account be <hi>kept enerie day:</hi> and <hi>That which thou doeſt in a matter of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12751:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:12751:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:12751:28"/>money, which is, that thou ſuffereſt not two daies to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſse thee without reckoning with thy ſeruant, leſt forgetfulnes ſhould breede confuſion in the reckoning; doe the ſame alſo in matters</hi> of thy ſoule, <hi>and actions</hi> of thy life, <hi>euerie day.</hi> And the ſame Father, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vpon that Text,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 51.3.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſinne is euer before me,</hi> noteth, that the Saints in old time
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Virtutum ſuarum obliti, peccata ſola me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriâ retinebant: non, vt huius te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtatis homines, qui peccatorum ſuorum memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am exuunt,</hi> Chr. hom. 2. in pſal. 50. pag. 1003. D.</note> 
                  <hi>were vſed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their vertues, and remember their ſinnes; not as men now a daies</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doe vſe to doe, who put their ſinnes out of their remembrance.</hi> And heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he aduiſeth vs not long after, in the ſame Sermon;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Annon codice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domi habes, in quo quotidianas rationes ſcribas? Habe item co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicem in conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, et quotidiana peccata ſcribe. &amp;c.</hi> Chryſoſt. ibid p. 1004. D.</note> 
                  <hi>Haſt thou not a Booke in thine houſe,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wherein thou writeſt thy daily accounts? Haue alſo a like booke in thy conſcience, and write therein thy daily tranſgreſsions. I meane,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when thou layeſt thee downe vpon thy bed, — bring forth thy booke, and take an account of thy ſinnes.</hi> And to like purpoſe ſpeake many others, as may further be ſeene in the next rule following.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The time which learned and wiſe men haue allotted for this worke, is eſpecially in the euen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or at night: becauſe that time is a time of vacation and leiſure. For in the day time wee haue our trades to follow, and our markets to make, and our Law-ſuites to attend on, and our friends to talke with, and our families to prouide for; and one buſineſſe or other will euer be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the way, and interrupt vs: but the night is a time of priuatenes and retiredneſſe, when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of the world being ouerpaſſed, we haue the more freedome to conferre with our ſoules. To this purpoſe it is, that <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke the night
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12751:28"/>time to meditate in;
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.55.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue remembred thy name, O Lord, in the night, and haue kept thy Law.</hi> And that time he tooke to lament his ſinnes;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Euerie night</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I make my bed to ſwimme, and water my couch with my teares.</hi> And that time he tooke alſo to examine his ſoule in;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 77.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I call to remembrance my ſong in the night; I comune with mine own heart. &amp;c.</hi> And that time he biddeth vs alſo take for the like purpoſe;
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Commune with your owne heart vpon your bed, and be ſtill.</hi> Vpon which words of the Prophet, we haue this note giuen vs by St. <hi>Chryſoſtom:
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Poſt coenom inquit, quande ilis dormilum, quande eſtis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubituri, et nullo praeſonte, multae quies et ſilentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et nen ine inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbante profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da tranquillitas; excita iudicium conſcientiae. — Quande neque amicus intertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, nec famulus irritat, nec turba negotiorum vrget tunc vitae inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu astae ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exigite.</hi> Chryſo. Expoſ. in Pſal. 4.4. pag. 26. C, D.</note> What meaneth this</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that he ſaith, Commune with your bearts vpon your beds? &amp;c.</hi> And he anſwereth, It is this; <hi>After ſupper time, when ye are going to ſleepe, and are ready to lye downe on bed, and haue great quietneſſe and ſilence, without the preſence or diſturbance of any, then erect a Tribunall for the conſcience.</hi> And a little after; <hi>When neither friend doth diſturbe thee, nor ſeruants prouoke thee, nor multitude of buſineſses doth preſſe thee, then take account of thy life, what thou haſt done in the day time before.</hi> And the ſame Father in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in lecte tuo iaces, nec quiſquam eſt, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi negotium fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſas, antequam ſomnus irrepat, libellum in mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> produc, et peccatae tua teeum repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, dicens apud teipſum,</hi> Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid hodier no die, vel ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vel opere peecaui? Chryſoſt. Hom. 2. in Pſal. 50. pag. 1004, 1005.</note> 
                  <hi>When thou laieſt thee downe vpon thy bed, and no man is by to diſturbe thee, before ſleepe come on, bring forth the booke of thy conſcience, and recount thy ſinnes with thy ſelfe, ſaying to thy ſelfe, HAVE I THIS DAY OFFENDED IN WORD OR DEEDE?</hi> He addeth;
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urne tempore id faciend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſpacium non habes; verum et Praeſectorum metus, et ſodalium collequia, at negatiorum eura, et alendae prolis fludium, et vxoris procuratio, as parandae menſae ſollicitucle,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Idem Ibid. pag. 1005.</note> 
                  <hi>In the day thou haſt not time for this worke; but feare of Superiors, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12751:29"/>with friends, and care of buſineſſes, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſting for education of children, and prouiſion for wife, and preparation for diet, and a thouſand things beſide doe diſtract thee.</hi> And to like purpoſe S. <hi>Baſil,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Complete iam die, ommi<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> opere cùm corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, tum ſpiritus etiam abſoluto,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Baſil. to. 2. de Inſtit. Monarc. in fine, pag. 396. C.</note> When the day</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is ended, and buſineſſes are paſt, before reſt or ſleepe, it is expedient that euery mans conſcience ſhould be iudged of his owne heart. &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Dorotheus</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Docuerunt nos ſaepe patres noſtri, qúe pacto purgemus noſipſos per fingulos dies, vt ſcilicet in veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peram perſcrute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur nobiſcum, quomedo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actam diem exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerimus, et rur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum manè quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo nocte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</hi> Doroth. to. 1. Biblio. Patru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, edit. Graecol. Doctrina 11. pag. 814.</note> 
                  <hi>that it was a rule from their forefathers, how men ought to cleanſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that in the euening they ſhould queſtion them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, how they had paſſed the day, and againe in the morning, how they had paſſed the night.</hi> And <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sedeat iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus iuſtitia, ſtet rea et ſeipſum accuſans conſcientia. Neme te plus deligit; neme te fideliùs iudicabit. Manè praeteritae noctis fac a teipſo exactionem, et venturae diei tu tibi indicito cautionem. Veſpere diei praeteritae rationemexige, et ſuperuenientis noctis fac indictionem.</hi> Bernard. de vita ſolitar. ad fratres de Monte Dei. pag. 1029. D.</note> Let iuſtice ſit and iudge, let the conſcience ſtand impleaded and accuſing it ſelfe. No man loueth thee more, nor no man will iudge thee better. In the morning exact an account of the night paſt, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vpon thy ſelfe watchfulneſſe for the day to come. In the euening require a reckoning of the day paſt, and lay an iniunction for the night comming.</hi> And in like manner ſpeake other ſpirituall Maſters, who vndertake to preſcribe rules of a religious life: whereby it may be ſeene, how they doe general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree vpon it, as a receiued Principle, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night men ſhould take accounts and examine themſelues for the day paſt: but in the two laſt authorities we may further note, that beſides the accounting at night for the day paſt, they require alſo a reckoning each morning for the former night. And ſurely that is not to no purpoſe: for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12751:29"/>euen in the night reſerued for reſt, there do many times paſſe thoughts, affections, purpoſes, yea and ſome actions alſo, which as they doe well deſerue cenſure, ſo may eaſily be forgotten, if they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred till multitude of buſineſſes the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing haue bred a confuſion in the memorie.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a very fit time for this worke, when we haue beene about ſome important buſineſſe, in which there may bee occaſion either of doing good, or of offending in ſome ſpeciall manner. Thus <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iob. 1.4, 5.</note> when his ſonnes had beene feaſting, becauſe great cheere and much merriment are moſt times occaſions of ſome ſinne; therefore at their returne home, he called them together, and <hi>ſanctified them, and offered burnt offerings according to the number of them all. For Iob ſaid, It may be my ſonnes haue ſinned, and curſed God in their heart. Thus did Iob continually.</hi> And thus Chriſtians ſhould doe, when they returne from making pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes, or ſtriking of bargaines, or following of Law-ſuites, or feaſting with their friends, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating of controuerſies, or any other the like workes and imployments of moment, they ſhould call together their thoughts, and examine their hearts concerning all the former paſſages, and ſanctifie their ſoules by lamenting their ſinne, and purpoſing a better life.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is a fit time alſo to examine our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when we haue ſome ſpeciall occaſion to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues for God, or to intreate his fauour in ſome ſpeciall ſort. Thus the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when thy were in diſtreſſe, and ſighed to God for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12751:30"/>reliefe,
<note place="margin">Lam. 3.40.</note> they encourage each other, <hi>Let vs ſearch and try our wayes, and turne againe to the Lord.</hi> And S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when the Lords Supper was to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, becauſe it was a matter of great weight, and might breede much harme to the vnworthy Receiuer, therefore preſcribeth this rule of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to all that mind to partake of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe: and ſo let him eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup.</hi> And ſo in like maner, if we be in any diſtreſſe or danger by reaſon of our ſinnes, that is a fit time to examine our ſelues, that by ſerious repentance wee may goe to begge pardon. And if wee bee to receiue the bleſſed Supper of our Lord, then wee ſhould examine alſo; leſt being vnprepared for ſo holy a worke, we proue vnworthy partakers of Chriſts body. And if we keepe a faſting day, for the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of our ſoules, that is a fit time; that by taking a view of our ſinnes, we may bee the more deiected with ſorrow. And if we keepe a Sabbath day, or ſome great day of feſtiuity vnto the Lord, that alſo is a fit time; that our ſoules hauing by examination beene purged from our ſinnes, wee may bee prepared to heare and pray and praiſe God with attention and zeale. But eſpecially if we be caſt vpon our ſicke beds, in danger of death, and in expectation of our diſſolution, then is a moſt vrgent time to take accounts of our ſoules, that our reckonings may be made euen before we be called to account at Gods Tribunall ſeat. For as the <hi>tree falleth, ſo it lyeth:</hi> and if we dye vnpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, we ſhall be vnable to anſwere him who is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12751:30"/>the Iudge of quicke and dead. In theſe therefore, and all other caſes of like moment and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, there is great cauſe to vſe this worke.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, beſides thoſe daily and caſuall times, it is a conuenient time alſo, after ſome good ſpace paſſed in this manner, to examine our ſelues ouer againe; as for example, after a moneth or after a yeere to conſider our ſelues for the moneth or yeere laſt paſſed, that thereby we may ſee, how wee haue profited, or how wee haue decayed for that ſpace of time. For
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sicut non ſentimus quo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do creſcunt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra, proficit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, mutatur ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, nigredo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillorum albeſcit in canis; Haec quippe omnia, nobis neſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus, aguntur in nobis: ita mens noſtra per momenta vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendi ipſo curara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſu à ſemetipſa permutatur. &amp;c.</hi> Greg. Moral. lib. 25. cap. 6.</note> as our members grow, and our ſhape euery day changeth, and our blacke haires turne gray, while wee perceiue it not, nor can tell when and how theſe changes come; yet after ſome ſpace of time we may caſily diſcerne, that ſo we are changed: ſo it is in the ſtate of our ſoules; beſides the manifeſt changes of it, which doe appeare while they are in doing, there are certaine inſenſible alterations, which are not to be diſcerned, but after ſome continuance of time. And for the rectifying of theſe, it is neceſſary to take a more generall view of our ſoules, then in euery daies examination we can doe; that wee may ſee wherein we are better or worſe, or how our zeale is increaſed or decayed, ouer that which it was a moneth, or halfe a yeere, or a yeere, or longer time before. For by this meanes we ſhall not only ſee our groſſer and more apparent faults, but euen our decay of feruor and religion, which creepeth vpon vs vnawares, and ſo learne to blow the coales of zeale, and to ſtirre vp the grace of God that is in vs, that we may
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Apoc. 3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrengthen the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12751:31"/>things which remayne, and are ready to dye.</hi> For which purpoſe the Ancients haue beene accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to vſe the time of Lent, as I haue ſhewed in an
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Treatiſe of Faſting, chap. 10. pag. 129, &amp; 131.</note> other place more fully.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the benefits of this worke, or what good vſe it may ſerue a Chriſtian for.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing hitherto in ſome meaſure declared the nature of Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with the adjuncts appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto, I come now in the laſt place to conſider the benefits that we may reape by it: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof may animate vs to <hi>abound in this worke of the Lord,</hi> when we ſhall <hi>know that our labour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi> And for that purpoſe I haue gathered and obſerued theſe vſes following.</p>
               <p n="1">I.
<note place="margin">Examination is a good meanes for <hi>Repentance.</hi> 1. Reaſon.</note> It will be a good meanes to fit and leade vs to <hi>repentance</hi> and amendment: and that in two reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it will ſerue to <hi>diſcouer</hi> vnto vs our ſinnes, and make vs ſee our wretched and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition. For we (ſuch is our frailety and corruption) doe daily, yea hourely commit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinnes, which through heedleſſenes or vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, or ſtrength of paſſion, or becauſe wee are intent vpon ſome other buſineſſe which then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12751:31"/>vp all our thoughts; wee obſerue not, or diſcerne not for the preſent. But buſineſſes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the occaſions and tentations paſſed, when we are more free both from diſtraction and paſſion; if then wee take a time to bethinke our ſelues, and to recall all that is paſt; then our thoughts will be our owne, and we ſhall in cold blood be able to ſee many things, which before went vneſpied. Then, for example, we ſhall bee <q>able to tell our owne ſoules, Such a time I met with a bon-companion, and ouer-ſhot my ſelfe with exceſſe of drinke; and ſuch a time I met with a wanton Minion, who inueigled mee with her lookes, and I was enſnared with her loue; and ſuch a time I met with a croſſe-neighbour, and my heart did riſe againſt him at the very ſight of him; and at ſuch a time I met with ſome mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mates, and in our idle chatt I diſgraced my neighbour behinde his backe; and ſuch a time, when I was in praying to my God, my heart was wandring about the vanities of the world, or my ſelfe fell aſleepe while God was admoniſhing me of things belonging to my ſoule: and many times in one day I haue ſinned againſt God by vniuſt dealing with my neighbour. One I deceiued by a lye, and another by vnſound commodities, and a third by counterfeit and baſe money, and a fourth by faire promiſes and proteſtations which I neuer meant to performe.</q> And an hundred other ſuch ſinnes as theſe, wee might diſcouer in our ſelues within a ſhort time, if wee did take ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of our ſelues at conuenient times. And if
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12751:32"/>our ſinnes were once in this ſort ſet before our face, they would make vs tremble for feare, and bluſh for ſhame, and giue no reſt to our heads, nor ſlumber to our eyes, till by ſorrow and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, we had made our peace with our God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Examination rightly performed,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> will bee a meanes to leade vs to <hi>repentance,</hi> becauſe it vvill ſhew vs with what patience and long-ſuffering God hath borne with vs, and in what deſperate caſe our ſoules ſtood, but that God in mercy ſpared vs beyond our deſeruing. For it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that he might haue ſtricken vs dead many a time, while we were prouoking him by our ſins. For example, while we were drunke, and could not ſpeake a ready word; or while we were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying our vncleane luſts in the Harlots bed; or while we were abuſing Gods name by prophane oathes and execrations; or while we were taking a bribe to peruert Iuſtice; or while wee were telling a lye to vndermine our neighbours; then and at ſuch an inſtant God might haue cut vs off, and haue drawne vs to the Iudgement with a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot in our armes, or a blaſphemous oath in our mouthes, or a bribe of oppreſſion in our hands, or a murderous and malicious thought in our hearts: and if then God had taken vs away, as he tooke away
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 King. 16.9</note> 
                  <hi>Elah</hi> in his drunkenneſſe, and
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan. 5.2, 3, &amp;c. with ver. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi> in his prophaneneſſe, and
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Act. 12.21, 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Herod</hi> in his haughtineſſe, and
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Num. 25.6, 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi</hi> in their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe. &amp;c. Lord, what might haue become of my poore ſoule? Or, what could I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but to haue dyed in ſinne without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12751:32"/>and to haue liued euer after in torment without hope? But he hath ſpared me, and it is his mercy, thus by his patience to bring me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that I might be ſaued. Now what Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian heart would not tremble to thinke what great danger he hath eſcaped; and would not melt into teares to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what great merey he hath receiued? And what ſoule would not be moued hereby to haſten his repentance, either that hee might preuent all ſuch danger heereafter to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or that he might ſhew a thankfull heart to God, that hath ſpared him in ſuch manner?</p>
               <p>And in this ſort will Examination leade vs to <hi>repentance</hi> and amendment, if we vſe it diligently and in due order. And that is the firſt vſe for which this worke doth ſerue.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Secondly,
<note place="margin">Examination a meanes to <hi>preuent</hi> ſinne. 1. Reaſon.</note> it will be a good meanes to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent</hi> future ſinnes; and that in two reſpects alſo.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Becauſe the finding out of our former er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and the ſinnes that be paſt, will lay before our eyes our ſpeciall infirmities, and will make vs ſee both the corruptions that cleaue cloſeſt vnto vs, and the tentations that ofteneſt preuaile with vs. For if the accounts bee diligently made, one will finde, that hee is ſooneſt ouercome with pride; and another, that he is ofteneſt taken with luſt; and another with vaine-glory; and another with reuengefull thoughts; and euery one with ſomewhat, to which hee is inclined by nature or cuſtome, or to which hee is allured by ill compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and daily tentations, or to which he is forced by threatnings or feare of offending. And when
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12751:33"/>once we ſee how we were miſ-led, and what it was that deceiued or ouercame vs; we ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by learne how to diſcouer the danger, and how to arme our ſelues againſt the aſſault, and how to handle our weapons when occaſion ſhall require: &amp; euery former error will make vs more wiſe and more warie againſt the next onſet. For as among men, hee that findeth himſelfe to haue beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with faire words, will neuer truſt that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie any more; and as hee that hath beene cooze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by counterfeit wares, will learne by that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to iudge better of the like commodities for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward: ſo in the caſe of our ſoules, a wiſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, by euery errour that he hath committed and diſcouered, will learne more wiſdome to preuent the like danger.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Examination will bee a meanes to <hi>preuent</hi> ſinne,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> becauſe hauing humbled vs with ſorrow, it will make vs afraid of the like ſmart, and reſolute to ſtand out againſt all tentations. For we vſually ſay, that the <hi>childe</hi> that hath beene once burned in the flame, will feare to come neere the fire any more: and ſo when by diſcuſſing our conſcience, wee haue learned to condemne our ſelues, as wrete hed. caitifes vnworthy of any mercy, the ſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of that which is paſt will make vs afraid to come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the like danger for ener after. Nor will any men be ſo prone to offend, if hee know that once within 24 houres he moſt come to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and be cenſured by the iuſt ſentence of his owne conſcience. So St. <hi>Chryſoſtem,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Anima he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternum verita <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>udicium, ne can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem rurſus ſubeat ſententiam, et torqueatur et fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelletur, reddetur ad peccatum tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dior.</hi> Chryſoſt. in Pſal. 4. pag. 27. C.</note> The ſoule,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>being afraid of the ſentence that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12751:33"/>paſſed on him the day before, will bee more ſlow to offend, leſt he doe againe incurre the ſame cenſure, and be laſhed and beaten</hi> as before he was. And S. <hi>Ambroſe,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Dum dolemus admiſſa, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda excludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; et fit quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam de condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione culpae, diſciplina inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae.</hi> Ambroſ. tom. 4. de. Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. lib. 2. cap. 10. pag. 413.</note> While we bewaile ſinnes paſt, we exclude ſinnes to come: and the cenſuring of our euill doings, is a diſciplinating of vs to innocencie</hi> of life. And <hi>Seneca,</hi> bending himſelfe againſt the vice of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate anger, for the moderating or rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing of it, thinketh this worke of Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, in which we paſſe cenſure vpon our ſelues, will be moſt effectuall. For,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deſinet ira, et erit moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, quae ſeiet ſibi qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tidie ad Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem eſſe venion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> Seneca de Ira, lib. 3. cap. 36. p. 599.</note> 
                  <hi>Anger</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will ceaſe, and become more coole, when it knoweth it muſt come euery day before a Iudge</hi> that wil not ſpare it. But ſurely, no man will either ſhame himſelfe euery day before God and his owne conſcience, nor iudge and condemne himſelfe for his miſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, vnleſſe he both meane to amend them, and finde ſome ſweetneſſe and comfort in the practice of this vngratefull worke: in regard whereof, I may truly ſay, (and that ſhall be the clauſe of this point,) Either <hi>examining</hi> will make a man leaue his <hi>ſinning,</hi> or ſinning will make him leaue off ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Examination maketh vs <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> Iudges betweene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and our ſelues.</note> the due performance of this worke, will make vs more <hi>indifferent</hi> and more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in iudging of our neighbours and brethren: For if a man doe not ſift his ſoule, and diſtouer his owne corruption; ſelfe loue and pride, br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in mans nature euer ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall, will make him to ouer-weene himſelfe, and vnder-value o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And this is the chiefe reaſon why men are ſo fauourable in their owne cauſes, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12751:34"/>in other mens. But if men by ſifting their ſoules, haue diſcouered their ſinnes, the ſenſe of their owne wants, will make them more pittifull towards others: as St. <hi>Paul</hi> implyeth, when hee exhorteth men to meekenes towards other men from this conſideration, becauſe
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Tit. 3.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>themſelues were ſometimes vnwiſe, diſobedient, &amp;c.</hi> And from this,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Leſt themſelues alſo be tempted.</hi> And where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelfe,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> that <hi>hee was chiefe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> S. <hi>Bernard</hi> noteth,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> buc di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebat Paulus me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiendi praecipitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, ſed aeſtiman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di affectione. Qui enim perſectè ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ammando ſeipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intelligit, ſuo pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato nullius pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum par eſſe exiſtima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, quod non ſicut ſuum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligit.</hi> Bern. de vita ſolitar. ad fratres de Monte Dei. pag. 1020. I.</note> that he ſpake <hi>this not falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, out of raſhneſſe and temerity, but feelingly, and out of the ſenſe</hi> and <hi>eſteeme</hi> that hee had of his ſinnes. <hi>For he that by examining himſelfe, doth throughly vnderſtand himſelfe, thinketh no mans ſinne to bee equall to his owne, which hee knoweth not ſo well as his owne.</hi> And therefore, if men would careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performe this worke in examining themſelues, they would not raſhly condemne others without cauſe.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII.
<note n="*" place="margin">Examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>comforteth</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.</note> This daily reckoning with our ſelues, will be a meanes to ſtrengthen vs againſt <hi>deſpaire,</hi> and to comfort vs in a time of <hi>tentation</hi> and feare. For if the Deuill ſhall preſent our ſinnes before our face, and aggrauate them, that he may driue vs to deſpaire; then our former practice of this dutie will be a help to ſupport vs two waies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe by often reckoning with our ſoules, we haue gotten the true knowledge of our ſtates; we haue found out our ſins, both which they be, and of what quality they are: and therefore wee ſhall not ſo eaſily bee deceiued by Satan, if hee preſſe them beyond their pitch, and aggrauate
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12751:34"/>them beyond their condition, as in times of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe he vſually doth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe by this daily reckoning and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſelues, we haue made all euen between God and our ſoules. For hauing confeſſed our ſinnes, and cenſured our ſelues, and fled to God for forgiueneſſe, we haue his promiſe of remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pardon. And then whatſoeuer our ſinnes be, (as certainely they are both the fewer and the leſſer for the performance of this worke, but whatſoeuer they be) we know they cannot hurt vs, becauſe God hath forgiuen them. And theſe things will be vnto vs matter of great comfort in a time of conflict and diſtreſſe; at which time a little peace of conſcience will bee worth all the world. For whereas men that haue liued ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without caſting vp of their accounts, are in times of tentation ouerwhelmed with horrour, being neither able to giue comfort to themſelues, nor to receiue it from others: hee that hath vſed a daily reckoning with his ſoule, will bee moued at the ſight of his ſinnes, rather to bleſſe God for his mercy, becauſe he hath pardoned them, than to deſpaire of his mercy, for feare that he will not pardon them.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Fiftly and laſtly,
<note place="margin">Examination is a meanes to preuent Gods <hi>Iudgement.</hi>
                  </note> our iudging of our ſelues in this ſort, will be a meanes to preuent <hi>Gods</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uier <hi>Iudgement</hi> afterward. For God will haue our ſinnes to be diſcouered one way or other, and will haue vs to be conuicted and iudged for them: and if our ſelues doe
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Prou. 28.13. Pſal. 32.5. 1 Cor. 11.31. 1 Ioh. 1.9.</note> bolte them out, and produce them, he will couer them; and if we accuſe and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12751:35"/>condemne our ſelues, he will abſolue and acquit vs; and if wee puniſh our offences, he will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them. Whereupon St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lectum at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> quietem petitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, hoc iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ineas: idoneum enim ad hanc re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoc te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus eſt, &amp;c. Id ſi quotidie dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter facies, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribili futuri Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Tribunali lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus aſsiſtes.</hi> Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. Hom. 43. in Matth. pag. 398. B.</note> 
                  <hi>if a man doe diligently euery day per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for me this worke of examination, he may ſtand with comfort before the dreadfull Barre</hi> of the great Iudge. But if we neglect this dutie, or ſlubber it ouer without care, he will take it into his own hands, and will performe it to the purpoſe: hee
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>will ſearch Ieruſalem with candles;</hi> and hee
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 50.21.</note> 
                  <hi>will reproue the vngodly, and ſet his ſinnes in order before his eyes:</hi> and hee <hi>will
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eccles. 12. vlt.</note> bring euery worke into Iudgement, whether it bee good or euill:</hi> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall goe for nought, that hath beene done againſt his Law. For, [<hi>aut homine puniente, aut Deo iudicante plectentur;</hi>] <hi>they muſt bee puniſhed either by our owne cenſure, or by the ſentence of God,</hi> who is the great Iudge of all the world. And in this ſort, our reckoning with our ſelues will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Gods iudging of vs at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like be the benefits which wee may reape by this exerciſe.</p>
               <p>Out of the conſideration of all which, I thinke I may iuſtly apply to this worke of Examination, that which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake of Gods Word deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Iſraelites;
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Deut. 32.47.</note> 
                  <hi>It is no vaine thing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs; becauſe it is our life, and through this thing wee may prolong our daies,</hi> in a bleſſed and happy ſtate for euermore. And this bare conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is argument enough, both to commend the neceſſity of the worke, and to command our diligence and care for the practice of it. But yet
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12751:35"/>to ſet a little more edge vpon our affections, we may hence deduce three conſiderations, applicable to our practice and ſtate of life.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Wee may hereeby ſee what the cauſe is, why moſt of vs, notwithſtanding our hearing and reading and praying and communicating, yet do rather <hi>decay</hi> than <hi>thriue</hi> in grace. For though I will not deny, but this defect may be aſcribed to ſome other cauſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; yet ſeeing Examination is ſo vſefull for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſo powerfull for amendment and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, the neglect of this muſt needes breed a great defect of grace: euen as the abſence of the ſunne, which is the fountaine of heate, maketh way for froſt and ſnow in the world. Nor is it any maruell that negligence in accounting produceth ſuch decay in our ſoules; for euen the like negligence in taking of accounts in our Trades, doth breede an euident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay in our worldly eſtates. For if wee ſhould paſſe dayes and weekes and moneths, without accounting our receipts and expenſes, euery cunning Chapman abroad would ouer-reach vs, &amp; euery falſe ſeruant at home might rob vs, while we thought on no harme, nor perceiued how or wherein wee were wronged. Now there is no chapman ſo craftie to deceiue, as the Deuill is; nor any ſeruant ſo falſe to his maſter, as our owne hearts are to vs: and therefore if wee paſſe daies and weekes and moneths, yea and yeeres too, without examining our conſciences, and calling our hearts to account, as moſt of vs doe; it is no maruell if wee decay in goodneſſe euery day, till at length we proue Banckrupts: nay rather it were a wonder if we ſhould long ſubſiſt, without being vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12751:36"/>vndone. Ceaſe then to maruell that there is ſo little <hi>conſcience</hi> in the world, ſo long as wee know that there is no more <hi>examining</hi> of the conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We may obſerue heere a reaſon, why God doth many times lay <hi>croſſes</hi> vpon vs; and though we pray and faſt and call for mercy, yet finde not that eaſe nor that deliuerance which we expect. For if Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination be ſo effectuall for remouing of GODS Iudgements, as hath beene ſhewne; then certainely if Gods anger doe continue vpon vs, and his hand be ſtretched out ſtill; it is an euident ſigne, that wee haue not iudged our ſelues, nor erected a Tribunall for the conſcience within vs, as in duty and in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wee ſhould haue done. Thus the Prophet threateneth the Iewes with Iudgements, becauſe <hi>no man repented him of his wickedneſſe,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 8.6.</note> ſaying What haue I done?</hi> implying, that as pardon cannot be expected without repentance, ſo repentance cannot be hoped for without examination and queſtioning with our ſoules. And therfore we need not maruell that Gods Iudgements are continued vpon vs, ſeeing we neuer take care to paſſe iudgement vpon our ſelues.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We may hereby ſee, how it commeth to paſſe that many men haue groſſe and conſpicuous faults, which themſelues diſcerne not, though euery child abroad can point at them and diſplay them. For if Examination be ſo good a meanes to repreſent our ſinnes, as in a glaſſe, vnto vs; then they which ſee not their open ſinnes, are not accuſtomed to make vſe of this meanes. And therefore, as when we ſee a man come abroad with ſome notable deformity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12751:36"/>his face, we may conelude that that man hath not lately looked himſelfe in his glaſſe: ſo if we ſee a man blinde in iudging of his owne ſinnes, which are to others as conſpicuous as the ſpots in a mans face, we may build vpon it, that man doth not vſe to looke himſelfe in the glaſſe of his conſcience, and by Examination to take a view what his deformities are.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Wee may hence gather matter of <hi>encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to breake thorow all difficulties, and to ſhake off our wonted drowſineſſe, that we may with ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie and perſeuerance go thorow with this worke. For if Examination be ſo neceſſary for repentance &amp; reformation: and ſo effectuall to breede vs comfort in our greateſt agonie, &amp; to avert Gods Iudgements for our ſinnes: then euery wiſe man will conclude, that this is a worke as neceſſary as his daily foode. For ſay that a man cared not for grace and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (which were a moſt deſperate and graceleſſe reſolution, yet ſay a man cared not for theſe:) is there any man liuing, that would not bee glad of ſome comfort when he lyeth a dying, or would not labour to be freed from the plagues that God powr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon vnrepentant ſinners? Let vs then but ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly minde theſe gracious effects of a ſtrict accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with our ſoules, and I hope we ſhall not proue ſo graceleſſe, as to refuſe our own mercy, and wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to caſt away thoſe precious ſoules, which Chriſt hath purchaſed at ſo deere a rate. I beſeech then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian, that either deſireth heauen, or feareth hell, that if hee haue beene negligent in this dutie heeretofore, he now at length begin a due and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12751:37"/>performance of it; and euen double his future care, that he may redeeme his former negligence: remembring withall, if ſtill he goe on notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all admonitions, that <hi>Sextius</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> heathen men, that were woont to examine themſelues euery day, will riſe vp in iudgement againſt ſlothfull Chriſtians, that paſſe on day by day, without euer taking account of their doings. Yea we may conſider further, that euen our ſelues ſhall riſe vp againſt our ſelues at the laſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and by our care for our ſtates in the world, condemne our careleſſenes for the ſtates of our ſoules. For if we know it to be ſo needfull for our worldly ſtates, to keepe an account of our expenſes and receipts; what excuſe can we haue for our ſelues, that we haue for many dayes and weekes, neuer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any account of our liues and conſciences? Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinketh, euery ſuch thought ſhould pierce the heart of any Chriſtian: and therfore haue I touched them, that we may be at laſt inwardly touched with a feeling of our owne want; and deſire of God that he will open our eyes, that we may ſee what is behoofefull for vs; and enflame our hearts, that wee may follow after it.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:12751:37"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
